Register of the Boris T. Pash papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Boris T. Pash papers
1892-1989
72033
Hoover Institution Archives
6 manuscript boxes, 5 envelopes, 3 albums, 46 motion picture film reels (10.9 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, orders, writings, photographs, motion picture film, and printed matter relating to the naval forces of General Nikolay Yudenich during the Russian Civil War; the Russian refugee camp in Wünsdorf, Germany, in 1922; American military intelligence service activities, including the Baja Peninsula mission to investigate the possible establishment of a Japanese base in Mexico in 1942 and the Alsos mission to determine the status of German nuclear development in 1944-1945; and to allegations made in 1975 of the involvement of Boris T. Pash with Central Intelligence Agency assassination plots. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Pash, Boris T., 1900-1995.
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Use copies of some motion picture material in this collection are available for immediate access. To listen to sound recordings or to view other videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1972, with several increments received in subsequent years.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
1900 June 20 Born, San Francisco, California
1918-1920 Volunteer, Russian Imperial Army and Navy
1918-1922 Member, The International Committee of Young Men's Christian Associations
1920 Employed by the American Red Cross, South Russian Unit, Sevastopol and Theodosia, Russia
1924 Graduated from Springfield College, Massachusetts, B.P.E. (Bachelor of Physical Education)
1924-1940 Chairman, Hollywood High School Athletic Department
1939 Graduated from University of Southern California, M.S. (Education)
1940-1943 Chief of Military Intelligence, U.S. Army, 9th Corps, Presidio of San Francisco
1943-1945 Commanding Officer of the Alsos Mission
1946-1947 Foreign Liaison Section Chief for Supreme Commander, Allied Powers, Japan
1948-1951 Employed by the Central Intelligence Agency
1952-1953 Special Forces, U.S. Forces, Austria
1953-1956 Deputy Assistant Chief of Staff for Intelligence, 6th Army
1956-1957 Staff member, Office of the Assistant Secretary of Defense for Guided Missiles
1957 Retired from military service
1995 Died
Scope and Content Note
The Boris T. Pash papers reflect the military career of Pash from his time as a volunteer in the Russian Imperial Army and Navy in 1918 through his retirement as a colonel in the U.S. Army in 1957.
Of special interest are the documents relating to the Alsos Mission, a U.S. Army intelligence unit based in Europe in 1944-1945, of which Boris Pash was commanding officer and whose object was to determine the status of German nuclear development. In addition to the manuscript material in the Alsos Mission file, there is a large number of photographs on the mission in the photographs series, including prints of the liberation of Paris and the surrender of Thanheim, Germany.
Also of interest are materials relating to the Foreign Liaison Section for the Supreme Commander of the Allied Powers during the postwar occupation of Japan, 1945-1948, found in the subject file. See also, among the photographs, prints of Soviet armed forces in Tokyo.
Yudenich, Nikolay Nikolayevich, 1862-1933.; United States. Army--Officers.; United States. Central Intelligence Agency.; Atomic bomb.; Refugees.; Russians--Germany.; Secret service--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Germany.; World War, 1939-1945--Mexico.; World War, 1939-1945--Secret service.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Naval operations.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Refugees.; Motion pictures.
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1918-1975 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Clippings, letters, press releases, and other material reflecting the military career and civilian life of Boris Pash, arranged chronologically.
  - 1918-1949 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - 1950-1975 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1892-1989 (Box 1)
  Letters and telegrams, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Unidentified
    - 1892-1893 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - 1951-1989 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - American Red Cross, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Anderson, H. D., 1925 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Barnes, John, 1975 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Borah, William E., 1929 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Brander(?), Peter, 1930 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Coney, 1942 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Devers, Jacob L., 1963 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Einstein, Albert, 1939 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1963 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Emel'ianov, Ivan Vasil'evich, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Gerlach, Walther, 1975 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Golunsky, S. A., 1946 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Goudsmit, Samuel A., 1976 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Hambro, Charles, 1955 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Heisenberg, Professor, 1955 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Hermann, Armin, 1976 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Hoover, John Edgar, 1951 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - International Committee of the Young Men's Christian Associations, 1918-1922 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Johnson, Jesse, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Pierce, E. C., 1945 (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Polette, Andre, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Robb, Roger, 1954 (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Sinclair, Upton, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - Societe Generale Metallurgique de Hoboken, 1944 (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - Thomson, E. F., 1953 (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - U.S. Atomic Energy Commission, 1954 (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - Willoughby, C. A., 1949 (Box-folder 1: 31)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1959-1981 (Box 1)
  Speeches and writings by Boris Pash, arranged chronologically.
  - Handwritten notes on the 1920 evacuation of Crimea, undated (Box-folder 1: 32)
  - "Checkmate,", 1955 December 15 (Box-folder 1: 33)
    Typescript.
  - "Checkmate! How the Soviets Tried to Take Over the Japanese Orthodox Church," The American Legion Magazine, 1958 April (Box-folder 1: 34)
    Printed copy.
  - "Why the Mental Panic?,", 1959 March 19 (Box-folder 1: 35)
  - "Where Is the Soviet Union?,", 1961 (Box-folder 1: 36)
    Holograph.
  - "Communication,", 1963 (Box-folder 1: 37)
  - The Alsos Mission, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 38)
    Printed copy of review.
  - Statement to the U.S. Senate Select Committee on Intelligence, 1976 January 7 (Box-folder 1: 39)
  - Statement to the U.S. Congressional Commission on Wartime Relocation of Persons of Japanese Background in the U.S. at a public hearing, 1981 August 11 (Box-folder 1: 40)
- ALSOS MISSION FILE, 1943-1976 (Boxes 1-3)
  Correspondence, memoranda, diary, reports, notes, clippings, and other material relating to the operations of the Alsos Mission, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - General
    Correspondence, memoranda, orders, reports, notes, clippings, printed matter, and other material.
    - Undated (Box-folder 1: 41)
    - 1943 (Box-folder 1: 42)
    - 1944 (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
    - 1945 (Box-folder 2: 3-4)
  - Article by V. Gilenson, 1962 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    Relates to U.S. military intelligence, including the Alsos Mission, during World War II.
  - Chronology (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Diary (Germany), 1945 March-July (Box-folder 2: 7)
    Written by an unidentified member of the Alsos Mission.
  - History (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - List of personnel of interest (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Subject file
    - DSM Project (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - Exposure to radioactivity (Box-folder 2: 11)
    - Radium supply (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - Recommendations
      - Legion of Merit Award, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 13)
      - Distinguished Service Medal, 1976 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - World War, 1939-1945
      - Germany (Box-folder 3: 2)
      - Military attaches - United States, 1945 April-May (Box-folder 3: 3)
        Memoranda of the U.S. Military Attache in London.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1894-1976 (Boxes 3-4)
  Correspondence, memoranda, orders, reports, and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Baja Peninsula Intelligence Mission, 1942 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    Correspondence, maps, and progress reports.
  - Espionage, 1947 January 20 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    Memorandum. Includes case of suspected German agent Dr. Kayl.
  - Heisenberg, Werner, 1943 October 15 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    Certificate signed by Adolf Hitler awarding Heisenberg the 1st class cross for war service.
  - Japan - History - Allied occupation, 1945-1952, Kurganov, Oskar, Amerikantsy v Iaponii, Sovetskii pisatel', Leningrad, 1947 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Kulaev, Ivan Vasil'evich (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Leningrad (Box-folder 3: 9)
    Maps.
  - Nikolaevskii Engineering Adademy, required courses for entrance, 1894 February (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Russkaia Pravoslavnaia Tserkov' - United States, 1963 (Box-folder 3: 11)
    Dedication of the Russian Orthodox Church of St. Nicholas, Washington, D.C.
  - Siberia (Russia) - History - Revolution, 1917-1921, undated (Box-folder 3: 12)
    Typescript by Gail Berg Reitzel, entitled "Shifting Scenes in Siberia."
  - Soviet Union - History - Revolution, 1917-1921
    - General (Box-folder 3: 13-14)
    - American National Red Cross operations, 1920 (Box-folder 3: 15)
    - Evacuation of Crimea
      - 1919 (Box-folder 3: 16)
      - 1920 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Subversive activities - Soviet Union (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Foreign Liaison Section, Tokyo, 1946-1948 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    Correspondence, memoranda, and reports relating to Soviet diplomatic and military personnel in Japan.
  - World War, 1939-1945
    - France - Paris (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - U.S. Army. 6th Army Group. G-3 Section. "World War II - Final Report,", 1945 July (Box-folder 4: 5-6)
  - Miscellany (Box-folder 4: 7)
- SLIDES, 1963 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  21 color slides depicting the dedication ceremony of the Russian Orthodox Church of St. Nicolas in Washington, D.C.
- MEMORABILIA, undated (Box-folder 4: 9)
  Five military insignia patches.
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1916-1963 (Boxes 4-6, Photo file)
  Photographs depicting the private life and military career of Boris Pash, arranged by subject.
  - 1 album of 105 prints depicting Boris Pash and family and Russian military personnel, 1916-1933 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - 38 postcards depicting various scenes in Russia, including Chernigov and Nizhnii-Novgorod, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - 7 prints depicting the evacuation of Crimea, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - 38 prints depicting operations of the Alsos Mission, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - 48 prints depicting operations of the Alsos Mission, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - 73 prints depicting operations of the Alsos Mission, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - 63 prints depicting operations of the Alsos Mission, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - 48 prints depicting scenes in Japan during the Allied Occupation, 1946-1948 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    Includes prints of Soviet and U.S. military personnel.
  - 32 prints of Boris Pash and others in Panama, 1950s (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - 32 prints depicting scenes in the Soviet Union, 1917-1921 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - 64 prints depicting U.S. armed forces in Germany, 1943-1947 (Box-folder 5: 10-11)
  - 8 prints depicting U.S. armed forces in France after World War II, circa 1946-1948 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - 6 prints of Boris Pash and others after his retirement from the military, 1960s-1970s (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - 35 prints depicting U.S. armed forces in France and Germany, 1945 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - 211 prints from a photo album relating to the Alsos Mission, 1944-1945 (Envelope A-B)
    Includes photos of Paris at the time of its liberation and the surrender of Thanheim, Germany.
  - 13 prints of Russian Imperial Navy training ships in the Baltic and Black Seas, and scenes of a Russian refugee camp in Wunsdorf, Germany, 1905-1907, 1922 (Envelope C)
  - 1 album of 132 prints depicting Boris Pash's military service under General N. Yudenich, White Russian Naval Forces, 1920-1923 (Album fD)
  - 2 albums of prints depicting the Russian refugee camp in Wunsdorf, Germany, 1922 (Album fE, fF)
  - 32 negatives of photographs taken of each page of the album described in "D" above (Envelope G)
  - 8 prints of a social event sponsored by the Foreign Liaison Section, Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, for representatives of the Four Power Occupational Forces, circa 1947 (Envelope H)
- MOTION PICTURE FILM, 1936-1945 (Film shelf)
  46 motion picture reels (includes duplicates) primarily depicting U.S. military operations in Europe.
  - Reel 1: Nr. 1 of numbered cans - 16mm film, 250 feet, 1936
  - Reel 2: Nr. 2 of numbered cans - 16mm film, 250 feet, 1937
  - Reel 3: World news, arms race, Spanish Civil War, annexation of Austria, Nr. 3 of numbered cans - 16mm film, 400 feet, 1937-1938
  - Reel 4: Monatsschau, Nr. 4 of numbered cans - 16mm film, 400 feet, 1938
  - Reel 5: Nr. 5 of numbered cans - 16mm film, 380 feet, 1938-1939
  - Reel 6: Construction of Siegfried Line, Nr. 6 of numbered cans - 16mm film, 450 feet, 1939
  - Reel 7: Bombing of England, submarine operations, Nazi heavy cruiser - 16mm film, 500 feet, 1939
  - Reel 8: Battle for Flanders, Armistice signing - 16mm film, 375 feet
  - Reel 9: Nazi entry into Paris, Nazi conquest of France, Armistice signing at Compiegne, top-Nazi entry into Paris (second copy) - two 16mm film reels, 150 feet, 1940
  - Reel 10: Conquest of Belgium, war in Poland - 16mm film, 500 feet, 1940
  - Reel 11: Five-day conquest of Holland - 16mm film, 100 feet
  - Reel 12: North Sea Battle, attack on Crete, advance into the Soviet Union, Minsk - 16mm film, 200 feet, 1940
  - Reel 13: North Sea Battle, attack on Crete, advance into the Soviet Union, Minsk - 16mm film, 25 feet
  - No. 13: North Sea Battle, attack on Crete, advance into the Soviet Union, Minsk - 16mm film, 475 feet
  - Reel 14: "World War II Assault on the Maginot Line," produced by Degeto - 16mm film, 200 feet
  - Reel 15: Alsos Mission, reel 1 - 16mm film, 450 feet
    Access
    Use copy available on-site for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 72033_f_0002488_r02_pt01.
  - Reel 16: Alsos Mission, reel 2 - 16mm film, 450 feet
    Use copy available on-site for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 72033_f_0002488_r02_pt02.
  - Reel 17: Alsos Mission, reel 3 - 16mm film, 420 feet
    Use copy available on-site for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 72033_f_0002488_r02_pt03.
  - Reel 18: Alsos Mission, reel 4 - 8mm film, 400 feet
    Use copy available on-site for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 72033_f_0002488_r02_pt04.
  - Reel 19: Copy 2, reel 1 / Alsos Mission, reel 5, reel 1 of 4 - 16mm film, 400 feet
  - Reel 20: Copy 2, reel 2 / Alsos Mission, reel 6, reel 2 of 4 - 16mm film, 400 feet
  - Reel 21: Copy 2, reel 3 / Alsos Mission, reel 7, reel 3 of 4 - 16mm film, 400 feet
  - Reel 22: Copy 2, reel 4 / Alsos Mission, reel 8, reel 4 of 4 / Nr. 22 of numbered cans - 16mm film, 375 feet
  - Olympische Spiels - 1936, launching of the Scharnhorst etc. - 1936, Nr. 10 - 1936, Nr. 9 - 1937, Nr. 10 - 1937 / Schmalfilm-Monatsschau - 1940: Nr. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 / “Deutschlands Heer" - 16mm film, 1936-1937, 1940
  - Duplicate II/ 1-6, reel 1 - 16mm film, 300 feet
  - Duplicate II/ 1-6, reel 2 - 16mm film, 875 feet
  - Duplicate II/ 1-6, reel 3 - 16mm film, 1150 feet
  - Olympics, rolls 1-7 - 16mm film, 1015 feet, 1936
  - Deutsche Reichswehr Manoverbilder - 16mm film, 50 feet
  - Cross section of Olympics (note from 1996: Film of aerial shot of battleship) - 16mm film, 50 feet, 1937
  - Pre WWII military planes firing practice (German) - 16mm film, 50 feet
  - From Steelblocks to Fine Tin - 16mm film, 50 feet
  - Schmalfilm-Monatsschau, Nr. 11 - 1935, Nr. 9 - 1936, Nr 11. - 1936 - three 16mm film reels, 1935-1936
  - Nazi Campaign in Poland, helgoland, Finnlands Hauptstadt (fragment) - three 16mm film reels
  - Papal Rome, the bomb plot against Hitler, air force exercise, Hitler’s birthday, Rome of the Oscars, paratroopers, birthday of the King of England - three 16mm film reels, 1936
- DECLASSIFIED U.S. GOVERNMENT RECORDS, 1944-1946 (Box 6, Reading room workstation)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Includes some interfiled unclassified government records. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover.
  - 2015 December release of records, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 6: 2-3)
    Diary, orders, correspondence, passes, and forms relating to J. M. Barnes, Royal Army Medical Corps (British Army), and his participation in the Alsos Mission.
    Also includes a map of Toulouse, France with negatives.
  - 2017 release of records, 1943-1945 (Reading room workstation)
    Correspondence and memoranda related to Pash's military assignments and the Alsos Mission.
    - Memo from H. L. Allen, "Travel Orders,", 1943 December 14
    - Memo from W. C. McMillion, "Orders," regarding Pash assignment, 1944 April 4
    - Memo from W. C. McMillion, "Orders," regarding Pash assignment, 1944 April 25
    - Memo, "Movement Orders,", 1944 May 26
    - Memo from Russell S. Hahn, "Orders,", 1944 June 29
    - Memo from John S. Weckerling, "Commendation on ALSOS Mission Report of 4 March 1944,", 1944 July 25
    - Letter from J. C. Hunsaker to Assistant Chief of Staff, G-2, 1945 June 29
    - Letter from Charles Hornbro, 1945 July 26
    - Leslie R. Groves letter to Dr. Vannevar Bush, 1945 August 14
    - Vannevar Bush letter to Dr. S. A. Goudsmit, 1945 September 4
    - Vannevar Bush letter to Clayton Bissell, 1945 September 12
    - Memo from Feodor O. Schmidt, "Award for Colonel Boris T. Pash,", 1945 December 5
    - Memo from Pash to Chief, Military Intelligence Service, "Final Report, ALSOS Mission,", 1945 December 10